continue. So in the previous video we
have discussed about cluster and
the place where we have left is that now
we have multiple brokers
who will decide that okay this broker
one host this topic and for this topic
this partition has to be the leader and
this partition it need to have as a
follower broker two
[snorts] need to host this topic and for
this topic partition one should be the
leader and partition zero should be act
as a follower. So who decide this? So
that's where the controller comes into
the picture.
So controller you can say that it is
nothing different. It is again a broker
only but responsibilities you can uh you
can say that a roles are different.
Okay. So it's a special broker which
responsibilities are
creation of topic
each partition elect partition leader
and follower
detect broker failure. Okay notify all
broker about the changes. So you can say
that they are act as a coordinator among
different brokers.
Okay. All the brokers keep on sending
the heartbeats to the controller and
controller can know that okay which
broker is up which broker is down and it
can do elect like okay
this broker should hold this partition
as a leader this as a follower okay if
this broker is down whatever the
partition it has okay that need to be
handed over to different broker
okay So in short controller manage the
cluster metadata
like info about topic about partition
about broker etc everything
and yes you can have a dedicated
controller you can say that a broker
with just one responsibility controller
only a broker can have like a dual
responsibility like a normal broker
which you can say that uh
uh produce uh producer and consumer
request also it will take care of it
plus controller [snorts] also it will
control other brokers also. Okay. So for
simplicity
whatever I will show I will like a
controller having one responsibility so
that it it would be easy to understand.
Okay. So now see this example.
I have a producer in the Kafka cluster.
I have multiple brokers. Let's say Kafka
broker one, Kafka broker two. Each Kafka
broker has topic and hold certain
partition, right? Some as leader and
some as followers
you have a consumer consumer group and
now here I have a controller.
Okay. So again it's again a broker only
but here I'm choosing that they have
only one responsibility of controlling
the brokers. That's all.
Okay.
So what does controller manage is
controller maintain?
What I told you cluster this Kafka
cluster metadata like information about
topic about partition about broker
everything. And where does it store? It
store this information is cluster
metadata log. So this broker you can say
that
has
this information cluster metadata lock
file.
Okay. So it holds this information. So
understand with this flow
let's say producer or from admin CLI you
raised a request to create a topic order
events you need to create an topic and
you want to have a three partition and
replication factor as two okay so order
events will have like partition zero
partition one partition two and
replication factor is two means one
leader one follower two one leader one
follower one leader one follower so
total six
so what producer see producer and admin
they can directly talk to broker not
controller in our scenario I'm taking
that controllers are like having only
one responsibility to manage broker okay
they will not fulfill producer and
consumer request so producer and admin
CLI from wherever you are creating the
topic they will talk to any broker cost
either this or this they don't care okay
they will say that hey
take this create topic request now what
broker will do is it will pass the
request to the active controller okay
let's say pass the request to this
controller this controller will create
topic decide which broker will have this
partition as leader and other as
follower so this will take care of And
it update this information into cluster
metadata. Cluster metadata has all the
informations about topics about
partition. Okay. For this topic, this
partition leader is this broker
and followers are present into this this
broker. It has all the information.
Okay. So it update into its cluster
metadata log and it also forward this
information to broker also. all the
different brokers. So it keeps broker up
to date.
Any changes happening in the cluster, it
happens via controller. Controller
update the cluster metadata log and
after that it will pass it to all the
brokers so that brokers are also up to
date. Okay.
So now again knowing about controller
few things comes to our mind.
What if this controller get failed?
Seems like a brain of the cluster,
right? What if this get fails?
Seems like a very important uh node.
So one thing, one answer which can come
to us is that hey we can have multiple
controllers like we have multiple
brokers we can have even multiple
controllers right controller one
controller two. Now the question is that
like okay for multiple brokers
controller is present to control them.
Now for multiple controllers do we need
another controller? It's like a loop.
Okay. Then that will become a
bottleneck. Then for that we need a
multiple instances.
Okay. So how this is handled?
So answer is KAF which is a modern and
the zookeeper which is legacy.
Okay. So I will focus on KF one because
zookeeper is now deprecated in latest
versions of Kafka.
So if you [clears throat] are using
Kafka greater than equals to 3.x uh now
zookeeper is deprecated in those and it
has been replaced with K raft Kafka
raft.
So both helps Kafka to manage cluster
metadata.
Okay. So this is very important part and
uh let's see this what how exactly this
K raft helps to resolve this
like we have a controller right so
currently this become our one controller
become our single point of failure. If
the controller goes down, you won't be
able to create a topic. Okay? And if any
broker goes down,
they there will be no one no controller
means they won't know if broker one is
down or not. Okay? So you can say that
currently it's a single point of failure
for us. So that's where kaf comes into
the picture.
Okay. But why zookeeper is deprecated is
because zookeeper is an external
distributed system which Kafka has to
deployed separately, monitor separately
and maintain separately apart from
Kafka. So it's an external
dependency for Kafka. So that's why they
have built their own kaf okay and you
can say that it it
lies with controller itself. Okay. So
there is no external dependency. So you
consider that when you when I'm talking
about controller, controller has this
koft logic also.
So both zookeeper and kaf uses consensus
algorithm.
Okay. Zookeeper use zap consensus. KF
uses raft consensus. That's why the name
KF Kafka raft. Now the question might
have come to you. What is consensus?
Okay. And why Kafka controller needed?
So problem for our problem is one
controller is bottleneck
because controller are the one which
stores the cluster metadata create
delete topic decide partition leader and
follower keep track of broker heartbeat
and timely detect any broker failure. If
any broker is failed, distribute its
topic and partition to other broker.
Keep other brokers up to date about
cluster information. These are some of
the responsibilities of controller.
Okay. And if this controller fails, the
cluster becomes unavailable. We cannot
create new topic. If any broker is down,
no one would be able to take its
responsibility apart on behalf of it.
And all cluster metadata information is
lost also because all the cluster
metadata information would be hold
within this controller.
So how this
raft consensus solve this.
Yeah. So we need first thing is multiple
controller. That's where now we have
controller one, controller 2, controller
3. One thing is clear. Now the same
question comes how now this who will
manage these three controllers. Okay we
have multiple broker broker one broker
two and we know that controller are
managing them but who will manage this
three controllers. So no one they will
follow raft
consensus algorithm. Okay. Each
controller has raft you can say that
implementation consensus implementation.
Okay. And only one controller is active
or act as a leader in one cluster. So in
one Kafka cluster, okay, only one
controller act as an active controller
and other controllers act as a standby
controller.
Okay. Now the question is who will
decide among controller who is leader
and who is follower. Again the same
question now comes. Okay. Now I am
saying that out of this three controller
only one has to be active and other
standby. But who will decide? You will
decide me will decide? No. What they
will follow raft consensus algorithm for
everything.
So
it's raft consensus means that uh voting
understand that it's kind of a voting.
Okay. So all the decision is taken by
quorum. Quorum means that majority of
the nodes. Now let's say that we have
three controllers.
So quarum would be nx2 + 1. So three so
we have three controllers, right? So 3x2
+ 1. So the quorum is that you got two
nodes. Yes, you can do that. Okay. So
these many controller node should agree
on any decision before it can be final.
Okay. So all the decision
that who would be the active controller
and who would be the standby. Okay.
So they will decide through quorum like
they do kind of a voting and if they get
a majority of the vote that decision
become final.
So for example quorum happen which
controller
should become active controller
any change is happening in the cluster
metadata that also be like pass through
quorum like majority of them should be
agree that yes this change should
happen. How internally raft algorithm
would be like that is out of the scope
like how internally raft algorithm work.
Okay. But now this flow what we have
seen earlier this one let's say create
topic request earlier controller updates
the cluster metadata. Now when the kaf
comes into the picture this flow become
little different.
Now let's see from producer or admin cla
you created first you created a topic
create topic request. Okay. And you want
three partition of this topic and
replication factor is two. The request
will goes to any broker. What any broker
will do is pass the request to active
controller. Broker will always talk to
active controller only.
Okay, it passed to active controller.
Now what active controller will do? It
will create topic.
It will decide
the leader and the follower partitions.
Okay, that partition zero
leader would be inside broker one and
partition zero follower would be inside
broker two. Like all this information it
will create and it will create metadata
record with offset say zero because now
metadata is getting changed. Uh some
information about broker partition has
need to be stored right. So it will
create new metadata entries.
Now what this controller will do it will
pass this metadata information to its KF
layer. So now here if you see that in
case of zookeeper it has to make let's
say network call to other service. Now
this kaf consensus is implemented within
controller itself. So it's part of a
controller you can say that. So it just
like invoke the method some kaf
consensus pass to its kaf layer.
Now what it will do it will initiate the
quorum process.
What this KF will do? It will call all
standby controllers KF methods. Okay.
Now it will have this like okay before
it initiate the column it will also do
that like it will update its local
cluster metadata law. this controller
one. Okay, when it pass this KF layer,
this KF at controller one update at
least its local cluster metadata log but
it's not committed yet. So it has its
own file like okay offset 99 I have
certain metadata record this is the new
metadata record I am writing let's say
offset is 100 I write it but it's not
committed yet because quorum has to be I
need to achieve a quorum I I need to
have a majority of the votes before I
commit so it write into a local file but
it's not committed and it have the last
committed offset is 99. Okay. If you are
already working with Kafka, then you
might be uh aware of the keyword uh
the word high [snorts] watermark.
Okay. But just like another like buzz
word like high watermark, it's nothing
but last committed offset. Okay. Till 99
means every controller agree
on this metadata change. But this offset
100 metadata change. Currently it's not
committed. So now it initiate the corum.
Now the request goes to each different
controllers. Okay. Now what they will do
is they will also have Kraft algorithm
runs and if they are also agree what
they will do is they will update their
cluster metadata local cluster metadata
too. So offset 99 offset 100 not
committed last committed is 99 for it
also. Similarly controller 3 its kaf
also agree with this changes. So it will
also update its local cluster metadata
offset 99 was already there. Now offset
100 which is coming
not committed yet because it doesn't
know this doesn't know whether quorum
has it is able to get the majority vote
or not but from it side yes I am okay it
updated its local record but not
committed and still last committed is 99
100 is not yet and they send a response
back to this active controller.
Now what it will do is it will check yes
majority
are able to write or majority I got the
majority like yes I got yes from them.
Okay they are okay with the changes. So
what ultimately it will do is commit.
Okay. So now here if you see that offset
in the local it will do this 100 offset
commit and it update its committed
offset 100. And now what it will do is
this cluster metadata log it will now
pass it to different broker. So now
broker one all the broker now has
information that okay broker one it's
taking care of this topic this partition
as a leader and this partition as a
follower. So now all knows
about the cluster metadata.
Now you might be thinking that okay what
about these controllers standby
controllers they still have not
committed right? So see
active controller need to send the
heartbeat to standby controller because
see if active controller goes down one
of the standby controller need to become
a active controller. So for that active
controller need to continuously send
heartbeat.
So with heartbeat it also send it's the
last committed offset also.
So the controller one is sending this
raft controller one raft sending the
heartbeat to controller 2 standby and
controller 3 standby raft and this also
send the last committed offset. So they
will get to know their raft logic has
all the algorithm which you don't have
to worry about and out of the like uh
scope for this
they will know that okay last committed
for the active controller is 100 over is
99 but they already have the record
that's why it's not copied it's
replicated they already have the record
now they just make it committed and
update their committed offset
so Whole
cluster metadata log is not get copied
only the
latest record. You can say that it
already has that but it get the
information that yes now the active
controller has committed.
Let us commit also. So there now all are
in sync with each other.
Okay. So now you got it very important
this K raft and why zookeeper is
deprecated. So KAFT is the one which
actually you can say that u manages the
controller
okay and takes care of all the quorum
and this cluster metadata storage like
earlier it is in committed once the
majority votes got then only it get
committed. So all this handles by KF now
okay and don't consider that KF is a
different than controller it's just like
part of a controller okay just like for
understanding that yes
it's like you can say controller has
business logic
create topic decide the leader follower
and this koft has you can say at storage
consensus logic.
Okay.
Now since we are talking about cluster
metadata, this is one of the important
cluster metadata information ISR insync
replica.
Okay,
again I will pause for one minute here.
If you are seeing that this getting more
complex don't worry uh for now like
cluster
okay ISR which we are going to see K
raft this small small subp parts let it
be clear and then I will show you one
complete flows also okay but we need to
understand this you can say that subp
part of Kafka 2 to understand it in
depth
Okay. So, ISR ISR is another important
cluster metadata.
So, who maintains the cluster metadata?
Controller. Controller also maintains
one more important cluster metadata is
ISR insync replica. What is that? For
each partition,
ISR represent the list of replica which
are fully caught up with leader.
For example, you have a topic order
event partition one. Replication factor
is three. What does replication factor
three means?
Leader and two followers.
Okay. So total three replicas.
So leader is let's say you have a broker
one and followers are broker two and
broker three. So what is the possible
insync replica
for this topic and this partition? So
for this partition of this topic ISR is
in sync replica. So these are all the
replicas which are currently let's say
in sync that's what it means that in
sync replicas for this partition
ISR is nothing but a list.
So it maintain a list of all the
replicas which are in sync for the
partition in simple way.
So for example if broker 3 lacks too
much let's say broker one leader it is
currently
latest offset is nine broker two
follower it is also at this offset.
Okay, because follower keep on
uh keep itself up to date with the
leader. It keep on sending the poll
request to the leader. Hey, any latest
update? Any latest update?
So, broker one knows broker the leader
broker means leader leader knows that
which follower is up to date in sync.
Okay. Now, let's say broker three
follower is out of the sync. Let's say
for I think five minutes broker one
leader hasn't heard or hasn't got any
poll request out of this. Okay. So it
got out of the sync. So what broker one
will do? Broker one will update the ISR
list. Hey, for this partition
for this partition one
of this topic the ISR is in sync
replicas are only broker one and broker
two. Broker 3 is temporarily removed
from ISR.
Okay.
Now the question is how
broker or how leader decide particular
follower is out of sync.
Okay. So there is one way that
you have this lag time. If replica
offset is close enough to leader log and
offset then you can say that it is in
sync and if it is within
so you have a lag time. Let's say if by
default is let's say if 30 second lag is
there between the leader and the
follower you can still say that yes they
are in sync. Okay. But if it is more
than 30 second we can say that now
follower is lagging
and how leader knows that because every
follower see Kafka is like pull based.
So follower is keep on pulling
it send a poll request. Hey any request
any request any latest updates. Okay
[snorts] so leader has the information.
Okay. As as soon as it find out that it
is lagging more than this time then it
considered as that
you are getting too much delayed and it
will remove it from the ISR.
So what it will do is the leader update
the ISR list and pass it to the
controller that hey this is the latest
updated ISR please update the metadata
cluster metadata.
Now you might be thinking hey what is
the use of this maintaining this list.
Now see this example now in the producer
is trying to publish an event.
So when producer publishing an event it
also sends this.
So
in the config we can set acknowledge
equals to zero or one or all.
So what does that mean? Now let's say
that
uh this is like currently it's null for
this topic.
Okay. And uh let's say for this topic
currently it's null. round robin let's
say partition two for example and
partition two let's say leader is
uh broker one okay so the request
ultimately goes to the broker one which
is the leader of this partition because
you know that leader is the only one
which handles write and read no
followers will do that so the write
request will always goes to the broker
which holds this partition leader.
Okay.
So what this will do it will just
persist it. It will persist the event in
the partition to logs. Okay. And uh and
in the partition two log it will hold in
one of its segment file. That is done.
But producer has used acknowledge all.
So now what this leader will do, it will
wait for all ISR replicas to update the
events. Now let's say broker 2, broker
3. Now let's say ISR is broker one,
broker two, broker 3. So it was three
replicas and all currently three
replicas are in sync for this partition.
So since producer has sent acknowledge
is equals to all. So all three rep all
three this replicas which is inside ISR
in sync replicas list they need to also
get updated. So when B b1 already got
it. So when B2 will fetch the latest
poll request promised and once it is su
successfully written it will send the
acknowledge. Similarly, it will do poll
and once successfully done, it will
acknowledge yes, I am also return. And
once all the replicas have written
successfully, then only it will send
publish event successfully.
Okay. So acknowledge zero means fire and
forget. Producer send the record to the
leader
and do not wait even for the leader also
whether leader success or able to
persisted or not it crash doesn't care
producer doesn't even care about the
leader also one means wait for the
leader at least okay so producer send
the request wait so leader will wait
till it's write into its logs properly
Okay, once it is done then it will send
a successfully published response. It
will not wait for all the replicas.
When you send all means leader plus
like all all other brokers which are
there into ISR.
Got it? Again now one question might
come to my mind. What if this ISR list
become empty? So see B3 got too much lag
so it got removed. B2 let's say B2 also
get lag from the leader so it can also
get removed. So one thing is can it be
empty? This ISR list cannot be empty.
Why? Because see two thing is it will
always have at least leader right? Maybe
it's replica.
Let's say uh replication factor is
three. Okay. So you have three replicas
into three different brokers. Now let's
say only replica two followers one
[snorts] leader. This followers might
get delayed. Okay. Or there is a lag. So
they might get removed from the ISR but
leaders can't. Right? So that is first.
ISR can never be empty. Another thing is
this is one more config minimum in sync
replica we have to tell. So
let's say you have put two. So means
apart from leader one more follower.
So in this case let's say
let's say this follower and this
follower goes down. Now in the insect
rep uh replica you have only one. So
okay now your producer send a request to
the broker which is a leader of
partition let's say one and
it has replicated successfully now it
will see ISR because
now you have put producer has used
acknowledge equals to all so means all
the replicas which are present into ISR
so currently it's only one B1
itself only leader but minimum in sync
replica is two. So what it will do is it
will fail. It will not be able to
process this request
because you have defined minimum inse uh
in sync replica you need two but now
this list has only one. So that also a
use case. So this list cannot be empty
at all.
Okay. So this is clear insync replicas
and k raft very important. Now in the
next part I will show you like one like
once the topic has been created then end
to end uh flow of producer right flow
and the consumer rate flow. So see you
in the next part. Bye.